[SPEAKER_00]: But then, something else is your situation on the general level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you see what I mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: You are mindful that you are here in the cave, sitting on the floor, while you're talking the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now you can have a thought of you, sitting in the cave, on the floor, talking dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that thought is particular for you now.
[SPEAKER_00]: While you're sitting in the cave, on the floor, talking about the dhamma, which remains general.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it can be the same thought,
[SPEAKER_00]: You can see it twicely or doubly, simultaneously.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can see the same thought on the particular level and you can see it on the same, like, same thought on a more general level.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's immediacy and reflection approach.
[SPEAKER_00]: But again, it's the same structure, same principle, same generality.
[SPEAKER_00]: What you should not do is confuse, then, the particular things for general and think that they are general.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they are particular.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it means if you see them as general, then their general became particular and now something else is general.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if it's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, you lose the sight of the general, you lose the sight of the mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's quite difficult, I think.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's very unnatural.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because natural means ignorant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Natural means going with the grain, as the Buddha referred to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the practice of dhamma goes against the grain, against the way of thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: That doesn't mean you kind of go mad and do crazy things.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just means you start thinking in the opposite direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this is the opposite direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: The most common thing is me, my cup, I want to drink the water.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now you start thinking indirectly.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can drink this water only because my situation allows it as a possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Water to be drank.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you start bypassing your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start making it redundant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because whether I want to drink water or not, the water is possible to be drank because of the situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why you can attend it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you realize, my sense of self that comes with this intention, I want to drink the water, depends upon that intention, I want to drink the water.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is given by this situation that it's not in my control.
[SPEAKER_00]: Therefore, my sense of self is something I can't control either.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means it's not my sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to define your situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can just know situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because you're already in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, all this is giving the example.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, the situation can be as general as you want, such as, I'm seated.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't even have to say it to thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just know already that you're seated.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, recognizing the situation, it's almost like on the level of knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if I ask you, what's your body posture now?
[SPEAKER_00]: You will know that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't have to get up in order to tell me that you were sitting down.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know you're sitting, so it's already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't need to keep it in the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, over-defining it means making it... approaching it in particular terms, which means you forget about general then.
[SPEAKER_02]: Forget about general.
[SPEAKER_02]: But when I think... when I think something about... suppose my situation was with all these people,
[SPEAKER_00]: Thinking is particular.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it can also be general.
[SPEAKER_00]: Depends what you think.
[SPEAKER_00]: Depends how you think.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, it doesn't mean that particular ceases.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, particular, in return, makes the general possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: The things that you see particularly,
[SPEAKER_00]: You realize, oh, it's because of this that my situation has arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, the particular things are defined as such because of your situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like two sticks.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't conceive them separate from each other.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even for an arahant, general and particular, that all remains the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Really?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's ignorance in regard to the structure and taking it as mine and everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: But yeah, of course, yeah, that's how it works.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean that you go into general and everything particular disappears.
[SPEAKER_00]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: General particular is the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: Putujana holds them, Arhant doesn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, jhāna, in particular, is the structure.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the same in arahant and in puthujjana.
[SPEAKER_00]: Puthujjana holds it as a result of his ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he has greed, aversion, delusion, and everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Arahant doesn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: But this whole relationship of sitting in the room, while seated, talking, it's the same for arahant or for puthujjana.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just that puthujjana takes it as mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, of course, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's because Bhūtujana takes things in his mind in regard to hunger or thirst, particular or general, he suffers.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ārahant doesn't take his mind, he doesn't suffer.
[SPEAKER_02]: For arahant, there's no self-view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, how could he see anything, something in particular?
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything must become general for arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, see, see the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fly is going to drink the water.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's only possible for you to attend and go and drink the water because it was available.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: None of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the same for an arahant and for a patujana.
[SPEAKER_00]: That makes no difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is indifferent to your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: The situation allowed for a drinkable water to be present and then, oh, I'm thirsty and I can drink the water.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, makes no difference whether you take it as mine or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it didn't come from you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It came from the general situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Arahant, how does he feel when he sees this?
[SPEAKER_00]: If he's thirsty, he feels significance of thirst.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then the water will make sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he knows that the water and the entire situation originates external to him, nothing to do with him.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whether he drinks the water or not, or while he drinks the water, he won't think of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Me and myself, and for me, because he understood the entire situation that already holds this particular drinking water experience in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He understood that is not self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's very... For me, still, I feel that... Why is it important to think this situation whatever?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because I...
[SPEAKER_02]: I think whatever it is that
[SPEAKER_02]: Because whatever you can feel, means, like, appearing as a bubble in the mind, whatever, whatever appears, I think if all of them, if I can see clearly, this everything's, without my control appearing everything, isn't, isn't it enough?
[SPEAKER_00]: But are you seeing yourself then?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or are you seeing just what's in front of you?
[SPEAKER_02]: These bubbles, if I can see that, cannot support self-view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, you're seeing the bubbles, but what is overseeing you're seeing?
[SPEAKER_02]: It means I'm standing outside.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means you're assuming yourself outside.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But by assuming these things in front of you, you put yourself out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means you don't really include your sense of self there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is seeing, there are bubbles.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are bubbles being seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're seeing everything, but you're not seeing the nature of seeing.
[SPEAKER_02]: If I could think that, only I can think as myself, as self-view, this is myself.
[SPEAKER_02]: If I can think that these bubbles, only I can think, regard as mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, my, my, my, I am, it's included in these bubbles.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, only because that only could cause... No, not quite, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, see, because when you say, the fact that bubbles already arise for you, no matter how you think them afterwards, the sense of self was already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're just managing the situation as opposed to uprooting it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, but self... you actually...
[SPEAKER_02]: I never see any other... really appearing as a bubble.
[SPEAKER_02]: These are actually calling as mine, not I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you will not.
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't see that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if it's... if the sense of self and sense of mind was to appear right in front of you so clearly, you wouldn't need a Buddha to become an Arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, what else I'm calling myself?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that depends, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can call any of the aggregates myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the thing is, you expect to find a particular thing that you called myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: But as I said, my sense of self is never particular, it's always general.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by refusing to look at the general level, you'll never see the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you expect to find it on the particular level.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it doesn't appear there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, no wonder you can't find your sense of self anywhere.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the fact that we can talk about your sense of self, means there is something being designated as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: Something very ambiguous, unclear, general, non-particular.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as such, it is real, it is present as a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to start seeing it like that, in order to be able to understand it like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you're just used to seeing things in front of you, bubbles, particular, sense of self never appears like that, which is why it's sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why you can never see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you see,
[SPEAKER_00]: Your general situation, which is where sense of self is, you see that as fully determined by these particular random bubbles.
[SPEAKER_00]: Indirectly, then you're already, like, uprooting your sense of self without directly looking at it, because you can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whenever you look directly, your sense of self is behind your look.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how it works.
[SPEAKER_02]: It means you need to see the relation, how these bubbles appeared.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no, that's not the relation.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, that's the explanation.
[SPEAKER_00]: How the bubbles appeared would be an explanation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the fact that bubbles are there, means you're in the situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fact that you're in the situation, means bubble can appear as bubble.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, sense yourself lingering somewhere in between.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can never look at it directly, because it's always behind your look.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, you learn to know where it is, without needing to look.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because looking will hide it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is for me not able to see what I'm calling myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not directly, not as a particular thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Indirectly, where your sense of self is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can't look at it directly, because the look comes from the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: I was feeling that whatever I feel inside the body or in the mind,
[SPEAKER_02]: Those things, actually, I was thinking as mine, myself, my feelings, my thought, everything.
[SPEAKER_02]: These, these all, like, all combined together.
[SPEAKER_02]: I was thinking, this here I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, see, like, even those things, like, your... the sense of mind is in regard to the things.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind is not in the things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, it's your attitude towards certain things that is the attitude of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that doesn't mean that everything is yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just means that some things... it's enough for some things to be regarded as mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sense of self is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sense of self is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even the sense of mind doesn't appear clearly right in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's also general in regard to a particular thing that you took as mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Attitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is attitude?
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you see your attitude particularly?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, here it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's an attitude in regard to things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a mental phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or just a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it is always there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't mean that it's permanent, but means it's in regard to everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you're looking at things in front of you, you're not seeing your attitude in regard to those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just seeing what's in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why it's wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: You leave your attitude out.
[SPEAKER_00]: But your attitude is that which needs to be changed, not the things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they were not a problem in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the bubbles, they're all bubbles, whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's your attitude in regard to them that you need to change, not them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Puputujana, always looking at everything, like a... based on self-view, everything... No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's not everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's me, me, I, and... Putujana takes his... takes not-self with self, or takes self with not-self, or takes self with self.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he cannot do... what he cannot do is take not-self with not-self.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is something like...
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm supposed to be looking at something.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything I'm thinking, I am looking at it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Arahant, but maybe he's not thinking, he is looking at it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, in a way you can say that, but he can think I am looking at this, but the thought of I am looking at this is not his.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not I.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not me.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no conceit.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then it's just the designation I am.
[SPEAKER_02]: What if I do?
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe I was thinking, I am doing everything, looking at... No, that's like when you're trying to, like, force, force the view over it, I am this, I am this, but no, you have to find yourself within that situation, and that's how you abandon it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if you're producing things in front of you constantly, you are doing that, which means that you, which is doing it, is out, it's not included there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it can never work.
[SPEAKER_02]: But for Patujana, it's not a temporal phenomenon, like a self-view is always there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, it should, in regard to the most fundamental aspects of the Agra, it's, yeah, it's always the same, which applies to Patujana.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when I say the most fundamental, I mean the most general.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he might not be taking this particular flask, carpet, cushion as mine, but he's taking the whole general situation, his body at least, as mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Therefore, whatever situation his body ends up being in, he'll imply his sense of self in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And whether through for me or not for me, or me, or both, or neither.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it needs to be undone in that indirect manner, through undoing the situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: To see things, actually, generally, is like something...
[SPEAKER_02]: I have to put something outside, you know, to see something, things, like... No, it's not the answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just have to discern it, where it is, how it is, without having to move it about in order to understand it.
[SPEAKER_00]: To the extent the thing has arisen, that's how and that's where you have to understand it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's discernment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Discerning what's given.
[SPEAKER_00]: The thing's given, but you have to discern within that what's given, how, like, what's important, what's impermanent, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's very new, actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't really know how much of this is now.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think, yeah, it's within the same ideas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's from the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he didn't invent anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: From the sutta?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: Really?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, if you read, you'll see all of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Explanations you can find in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, the suttas being so general, like, you know, Bhikkhu Bodhi calls the suttas to support his three-life interpretation, because he finds parts that have nothing to do with bodhichitta and pada, but he would call them for bodhichitta and pada.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, when he needs to, he would ignore the abstract principle just to support the view.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the suttas allow that because they're so profound and so general in their description that, actually,
[SPEAKER_00]: People can use them and misuse them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why, like, if you start thinking like this, then you can start reading the suttas in this way.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then they will read very differently.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then it will become apparent why, like, one sutta is enough for arahantry, if you fully understand it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Before you were reading sutta in different way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, before I was reading suttas like everybody else does.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Wise inspiration, but kind of product of folklore India, long time ago, ancient text type.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then I started reading in the Veera.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, then I started reading existential philosophy that was making lots of sense, in terms of intention, action, responsibility, feelings, anxiety, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then I started reading in the Veera.
[SPEAKER_00]: Talking about the suttas in those terms, and I realized, wow, you can actually... yes, you can read it as an ancient sacred text that just produced poetic inspiration, but you can also read it as an existential phenomenological description of experience right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you stop and think which of those two ways, either romantic inspiration,
[SPEAKER_00]: Or a phenomenological, accurate, actual description of your experience, which one of those two is most likely to make you an arahant, you realize it's the latter one.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you read as a description of the universal aspects of the experience, whether two and a half thousand years ago, whether now, whether two and a half thousand years later, still the same universal experience, you understand it like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you need is one sutta to become an arahant, if you fully understand it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether it's been spoken two millennia ago, or now, or ten millennia late, just makes no difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the same thing spoken.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Buddha said, when he discovered the dhamma, he realized, oh, it's like finding an ancient ancient path that was already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: He didn't invent himself nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's...
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why I say to people, like, you know, you might... you don't want to get... you don't need to get into all the philosophy and everything everybody talks about, but if you... at least if you get the attitude towards the suttas from him, you can't ask for more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, how to read them, how to approach them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it's very interesting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because then you read the suttas and you stop and think about every single sentence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, as I said, you read, oh, consciousness and da-da-da, and then, well, do I even know, putting the sutta aside, in my own terms, what consciousness is?
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how can I expect that that which I think consciousness is, is that which the Buddha talks about when he says consciousness?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you stop and think further, and you realize, well, if my thought of consciousness would correspond to Buddha's thought of consciousness, I would be an arahant, or at least a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I'm neither of those, therefore, when I think consciousness, that's not the consciousness that Buddha talks about.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you keep drilling, and drilling, and drilling.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, even if you did it, you'll come back to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you read it again.
[SPEAKER_00]: Many times.
[SPEAKER_02]: Very interesting.
[SPEAKER_02]: At the moment, they can't explain in such a way.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's very interesting.
[SPEAKER_02]: Wow.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, I haven't heard anybody speak like this before, like, in these ten years, so... You had no teacher, no, you said?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: No teacher.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I haven't even heard anybody resembling, like, this type of approach when they speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: This way of thinking, so...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not surprising that you haven't...
[SPEAKER_02]: Only through, through your experience and through your meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, through experience, through meditation, through the suttas, through, through, through pondering and understanding, you know, you, you, you, you, you get to see where people come from when they talk about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh, I haven't, yeah, I haven't really heard anybody even coming remotely from this direction, the direction that Navira was talking about, the direction that's implied in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: That doesn't mean that there aren't any, but just I haven't heard in the West where I live.
[SPEAKER_02]: There are some monks, they don't agree with the sutra.
[SPEAKER_02]: Some of them, they say that some of them are wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, well, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was so... such a long time ago when they were spoken.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you can't prove, you can't disapprove either.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when people come across some parts, they can't come to terms with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, they must have been introduced later.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, well, yeah... How do you feel?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you agree with it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I don't care.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, it's it's kind of irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it's it's a silly thing to do, because unless you're a sotāpanna, you have no criteria of what's right, what's wrong, which is why you're not a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Therefore, when you choose to ignore certain parts because you believe that they were introduced or whatever else, well, you're following your patujana's criteria.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's, again, you don't know for sure, but to be on the safe side,
[SPEAKER_00]: You take it all, you accept it all, just so that you can practice and hopefully get the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you get the right view, then certain things might become more apparent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I don't really know whether this came later or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if there are such parts, they won't pertain to the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: It might pertain to some story or some social relationship or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will not pertain to the four noble truths and the concept, the main concept.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just won't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if it does, you will know this is wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is not the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why, when you read Mahāyāna Sūtras, there's not a single Buddha word there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Really?
[SPEAKER_00]: It was stuff I read, at least, the Huineng and the Six Pārtya, Six Pārtya Huineng and Heart Sutra and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was just very strange.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, it's known, it's not debatable that it's introduced later by their own teachers and preachers.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the thing is, you know, there can be things introduced later
[SPEAKER_00]: New arahants coming and teaching in their own terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will still be the same dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if it isn't, it means it's not.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not arahants.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and, and, you know, you can see that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can see...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not a problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: One day, the Venerable Bhārata, he told me that if someone, any monk, disagrees in the sutra, then that's, that's, you must avoid such... Well, no, it depends.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if they're disagreeing, if they say, if they're disagreeing with the key concepts,
[SPEAKER_00]: If they're dismissing Pratītyasena Upādāna, like Bhikkhu Bodhi, yeah, you should dismiss him then.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you don't have to dismiss his scholarship, but his views, you should really consider them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, as I said, even without, you know, needing to be a sotāpanna or something, if you stop and think about it, well, even as an abstract principle of Pratītyasena Upādāna, it's still a principle within which the whole...
[SPEAKER_00]: The only reason it's abstract, it's because a person does not see directly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if anything, if you call something abstract principle, means that's something you didn't understand, which is why it is abstract.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's abstract only in regard to its content, not in its nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, principle is principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, oh, that principle is abstract for me, because I don't understand it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if everybody starts with this principle, and then you have somebody comes and dismisses the principle and gives you a different explanation, you should be doubtful of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or if somebody goes even further and blatantly says, no, I disagree with that sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, samādhiti sutta, I think that's all wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you should, like, you shouldn't waste your time speaking to them then, if they say such thing, because samādhiti sutta does not pertain to any traditional, any cultural, any product of the, you know, ancient India.
[SPEAKER_00]: It pertains to the Right View and the Noble Eightfold Path.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if somebody dismisses that, well, they're not really following the Buddha's teaching, even if they're monks.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, but there's no Buddha's teaching if someone doesn't agree with it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's different.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because what they're not agreeing, they're not agreeing with an interpretation of the Buddha's teaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't agree with the view of the Buddha's teaching.
[SPEAKER_02]: You say some are here, they don't agree.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, see, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: They might disagree or they might not be able to comprehend.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of the things Nyanavira was saying, but I think with little effort, they would understand the basic ideas, and they would know whether Nyanavira was or wasn't a Sotāpanna, if they were truly artists.
[SPEAKER_00]: But people often dismiss it entirely, while they're still... they know they're Putuginas, but they don't know that as Putuginas, they cannot know what's right, what's wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: I met quite a lot of monks like that, senior monks like that, who would know, who would openly say, oh, I haven't attained anything, but that wouldn't stop them from saying what you should do in terms of practice, which is a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't know yourself what you need to do in terms of to get the right view, how can you even conceive teaching somebody else to get the right view?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just mind-boggling contradiction that doesn't seem to stop them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, coming from the same place,
[SPEAKER_00]: If they come across something they don't like, they don't like the way it was put out, they don't like the way it was taught, displeases them or whatever, such as in Navidā's books and his views, they'll dismiss it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Knowing themselves they're putujana and they have no criteria for the true dismissal, they'll dismiss it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why they stay putujanas.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just how it works.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, but you don't know what's right, you don't know what's wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the element of faith is necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that faith should be, like, governed or guided or directed by intelligence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just blind faith, where you accept everything called Buddhism, but you discern and you think what is least likely to be wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know what's right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything might be wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is least likely to be wrong, and then I'll start putting my effort in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, if it's... if I was a little bit fortunate, if I was intelligent enough, I might have chosen the right thing, and with a sufficient amount of effort I put, I'll get a confirmation that it's the right thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why in the suttas the Buddha would refer to
[SPEAKER_00]: Satipaṭṭhāna is somebody who has a confirmed confidence in dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, they were confident, oh, this is least, this is most likely the correct thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, they had that thought confirmed when they became satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they know that they know.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, he... the faith gets replaced by confidence.
[SPEAKER_00]: It all becomes unshakable faith, which is not really faith anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's confidence.
[SPEAKER_00]: He knows that he knows.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he cannot even conceive, because the Buddha is the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dhamma is the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not... it's not that the Buddha is the person or something who happened to say something right.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha is that teaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they understood the teaching, they understood the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's inconceivable for them to now follow a different teacher.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when I say different teacher, I don't mean another monk who might be teaching the same, and then they have, OK, I'll listen to you a bit more, because you seem like they did follow Sariputta.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, when I say different teacher, I mean Christian, teaching Christian philosophy, Christian views, or Western science, for that matter, because that's almost like a religion today, or psychology.
[SPEAKER_00]: They wouldn't be able to adopt that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's a wrong view.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only way they could adopt any other teaching, if it's a teaching that's the same as the dharma, which would be the dharma.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's actually interesting.
[SPEAKER_02]: Some Christians, they can become a real... Not through Christianity.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not through Christianity.
[SPEAKER_02]: I heard Venerable Pāṇḍa told me that when Buddha was alive, at that time, they were Sotāpanna or something, and in this life, they were born as Christian or something, at least in Christian family.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, eh... something, anyway... No, that makes no difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, what view your family holds, and what heritage you're born in, that's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: What view you hold, and what teaching you follow, personally, to try to understand, that's what matters.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, somebody can might well be a Christian priest.
[SPEAKER_00]: If he ponders on impermanence, and suffering, and nature of not-self, he ponders on dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if he becomes an ārya, he becomes because of the dhamma, not because of his believing imaginary friend.
[SPEAKER_02]: After... if they become ārya, with being the Christian, all of those beliefs that the God... Well, they would see them as wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: Wrong?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, not even... like, they would see them as irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, the belief in God and everything, it's... not as much as it's wrong, but it's just irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_00]: It makes no difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, it makes difference for people who don't know and put their whole life in those beliefs, but if somebody understood the nature of suffering and freedom from it, belief... it just doesn't even apply, belief, in God anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: In Seattle, a Buddhist country with many people, they believe in astrology and the horoscope and everything.
[SPEAKER_02]: What's the problem?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's a superstition.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the most kind of primal attitude towards, you know, the unknown.
[SPEAKER_00]: People are superstitious.
[SPEAKER_00]: Magic and like, oh, omens and good signs and bad signs.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically like a
[SPEAKER_00]: Something people need to do in order to to quickly escape anxiety.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anxiety of an existing individual.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, you know, just being alive already means you're in a perilous situation, because you can die at any time and you have absolutely no say in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And just that single thought can freak people up, out, can make them mad, if they really... Like you... you just... you couldn't stop it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your whole world can end in a second, and you can't do anything about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the immediate response to that is, no, but it will all be good.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll believe.
[SPEAKER_00]: God will protect me, or universal energy will protect me, or my horoscope tell me I'll be fortunate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything like that, just to... just give it a little grain of hope to overcompensate and allows you enough to not look at the anxiety.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you keep looking, you'll go mad.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha did say that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, he said that if somebody experienced suffering rightly, correctly, that anxiety, open, clear, without any cover of the views and superstition and all sorts of other religions, there are only two outcomes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mental derangement or search.
[SPEAKER_00]: A noble search, they will bring that pain, and it would... like, if somebody is strong enough to not go mad, it would result in them looking for a medicine that can remove this pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the state the person needs to be in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, he needs to be open to the existential anxiety to such an extent that, yeah, there is a risk of madness, but that means there is also a possibility of the right search.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean the person actually has to go mad, but means the person has to stop covering it up through superstition, through horoscope, through empty beliefs, through magic, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mental weakness.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the thing is conflicting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which one?
[SPEAKER_01]: The astrology of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he... when he got... Oh, yeah, the auspicious signs.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, he didn't refuse it completely in terms of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's always 50-50, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it means 5 out of 10 can always get it right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I say this will happen or that will happen, well, one of the two outcomes will happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I have 50% of chance of being right.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha never dismissed that, but he never ever used it as a... like, in reference to... pertain to the core of the teaching and feelings of saṃsāra or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that also, like, begs the question, well, how did he use it then?
[SPEAKER_00]: In what sense?
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether it was like a real divine... Like, there is... there are people who could
[SPEAKER_00]: Even back in the day, who could develop, like, supernatural abilities, and they could see a future destination based on the current actions you're doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, there are people who can see your two or three next destinations based on the current actions you're doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are people who can see ten.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, and then if they say, well, this is your, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: Future projection, then that's true.
[SPEAKER_00]: But again, it's not set in stone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you change your behavior, you can change your future outcome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like with the current set of mental determinations and things you do and whether actions are wholesome and unwholesome, you are heading to heaven.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if that changes, if you start misbehaving and doing some unwholesome stuff, you won't be going to heaven.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes people see only one life ahead.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then they say... and then they see somebody here misbehaving, but they see his next life is heaven.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then they see somebody behaving, but they see his next life is also heaven.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then they say, oh, makes no difference whether you behave or you misbehave, you're reborn in heaven.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then another person comes and sees five lives ahead.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he says, well, yeah, he might be in the heaven next life, because actually in the previous life he did some good stuff, but next four lives are misery.
[SPEAKER_00]: The one who behaves, all five will be heaven.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he says, no, it matters how you behave, whether good or bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even those views are limited, but they all pertain to the external, like, nature of saṃsāra, what might be ahead of you, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not to the way to escape it, which is what the Buddha was concerned about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you're an Arahant, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No matter... and there was... he was...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think he was slightly mocking them, but he was also proving a point.
[SPEAKER_00]: There was that divine... he was... he would do this divine... divinations, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: He would look at the skull.
[SPEAKER_00]: They would give him a skull of a dead person and he would tap on it and do some things and they say, he is reborn in such and such place.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I think there must have been something to... he might have had some of the abilities to see the future rebirth, which doesn't... means nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Butujana can see future rebirths.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's no salvation.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just... if I tell you tomorrow, you'll most likely be home.
[SPEAKER_00]: In ten years, you might be... next life, you might be some... like at such-and-such place.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's... it's within the same nature of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if I tell you in five minutes you'll do this, and in, you know, five hundred lifetimes you'll do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a greater on a scale, but it's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when they brought this skull to this man of... of a monk who died, who was an arahant, he tapped it, and then he was confused, and then he... he kept tapping it, and he couldn't... he couldn't see anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like, well, that's because he's not reborn anyway.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's exactly that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, the thing is, but the problem is people don't take it like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: They take it as a setting stone divine, like completely blessed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I'm blessed because I was told.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: At the time when you were told, if that person who told you
[SPEAKER_00]: You could truly see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You were heading at the heavenly destination.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's because back then, your behavior was good.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they don't tell you that.
[SPEAKER_00]: They just tell you, you go to heaven and that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I spend the rest of my life thinking, I go to heaven no matter what I do.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly what Christians, what they've been doing, you know, the Crusaders' wars and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: You go plundering, raping, murdering, stealing, with the belief of you going to heaven.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you were told.
[SPEAKER_00]: But actually, even that depends on your right now actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you might... you will be better off if somebody tells you, if you behave wholesomely, if you don't give in to anger, don't give in to greed, don't give in to any aversion, you'll most likely go to heaven.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't need any special natural powers to know that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just need a simple intelligent reflection, which I started this talk with.
[SPEAKER_00]: When somebody thinks, well, whether I misbehave or not, if there's a future life or not, it's better to behave.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're better off if somebody tells you that, because then, for the rest of your life, you'll be doing things rightly, with that thought of a good rebirth.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha did say that, actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, behaving properly, keeping the sīla and virtues, goes to more fortunate destinations.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's better to be told than if somebody just tells you, oh, yes, you're heading to heaven, and you take it for granted.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if they truly knew that you were heading to heaven, they probably wouldn't just tell you you're heading to heaven.
[SPEAKER_00]: They would tell you you're heading to heaven if you keep behaving properly like you're doing now.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you... unless you hear that, then be a bit more doubtful, just in case.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, even if they're right or not, you can't tell, so it's better to be on the safe side.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's how the Buddha approached it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean there's absolutely nothing to it, but whatever it is, it still depends on what you do right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't really mean much.